Gregory Pincus Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Gregory Pincus Papers 1920-2006 (bulk 1950-1967)
MSS47993
Pincus, Gregory, 1903-1967
44,100 items
212 containers plus 4 oversize
86 linear feet
1 microfilm reel
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Biologist. Correspondence, diaries, speech, article, and book file, research files, and miscellaneous material relating to Pincus's life and career, especially his role in developing and testing the contraceptive pill.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Ercoli, Alberto--Correspondence.; Garcia, Celso-Ramon, 1921- --Correspondence.; Lasker, Mary--Correspondence.; McCormick, Katharine Dexter, 1875-1967--Correspondence.; Pincus, Gregory, 1903-1967.; Rice-Wray, Edris--Correspondence.; Rocamora, Hector--Correspondence.; Rock, John, 1890-1984--Correspondence.; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966--Correspondence.
Organizations
G.D. Searle & Co.--Correspondence.; Planned Parenthood Federation of America.; Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology.
Subjects
Birth control.; Contraception.; Contraceptives.; Human reproduction.; Oral contraceptives--Haiti--Testing.; Oral contraceptives--Puerto Rico--Testing.; Oral contraceptives.
Occupations
Biologists.
Provenance
The papers of Gregory Pincus, biologist, were given to the Library of Congress by Pincus and his family, 1966-2016.
Transfers
A video recording has been transferred to the Library's Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where it is identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Gregory Pincus are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on one reel. Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1903, Apr. 9 Born, Woodbind, N.J.
1924 B.S., Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
1924 Married Elizabeth Notkin
1927 M.S., Sc.D., Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1927 1930 Fellow, National Research Council
1930 1931 Instructor of biology, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1931 1938 Assistant professor of biology, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1936 Published The Eggs of Mammals. New York: Macmillan Co.
1937 1938 Visiting investigator, Cambridge University, Cambridge, England
1938 1945 Visiting professor of experimental zoology, Clark University, Worcester, Mass.
1939 1941 Guggenheim Fellow
1944 Established with Hudson Hoagland the Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology, Shrewsburg, Mass.
1944 1956 Director of laboratories, Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology, Shrewsburg, Mass.
1946 1950 Research professor of physiology, Tufts Medical School, Boston, Mass.
1950 1967 Research professor of biology, Boston University, Boston, Mass.
1956 1960 Chairman, Endocrinology Panel, Cancer Chemotherapy National Service Center, National Institutes of Health, Washington, D.C.
1956 1967 Research director, Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology
1960 Received Albert D. Lasker Award
1965 Published The Control of Fertility. New York: Academic Press
1967 Received American Medical Association Scientific Achievement Award
1967, Aug. 22 Died, Boston, Mass.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Gregory Goodwin Pincus (1903-1967) span the period 1920-2006, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the years 1950-1967. The collection consists of diaries, correspondence, writings, research files, and miscellaneous material relating to Pincus's life and career, especially his role in developing and testing the contraceptive pill. The papers are organized into nine series: Diaries; Personal Correspondence; Professional Correspondence; Speech, Article, and Book File; Research Material; Notebooks; Financial Papers; Miscellany; and Addition. The largest portion of the collection, the Professional Correspondence series, is compartmented into four subseries: General File, G. D. Searle & Company File, Cancer Chemotherapy National Service Center File, and Grants File.
Prominent in the General File subseries of the Professional Correspondence are materials pertaining to the Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology, which Pincus helped found, and the Planned Parenthood Federation of America. Among the studies documented are projects conducted by Pincus in Haiti and Puerto Rico while developing and testing the oral contraceptive. Correspondence and reports concern the women who participated in the project and note their experiences, side effects, and thoughts and feelings about the contraceptive pill. Significant correspondents include Alberto Ercoli, Celso-Ramon Garcia, Mary Lasker, Katherine Dexter McCormick, Edris Rice-Wray, Hector Rocamora, John Rock, and Margaret Sanger.
Files relating to the G. D. Searle & Company, which manufactured most of the compounds investigated by Pincus in the search for the oral contraceptives, document his relationship with Searle from as early as 1942, including research projects that predate its association with the pill. The files are primarily correspondence and include related material. The Grants File subseries of the Professional Correspondence documents the range of research grants provided Pincus and his staff from many sources.
Also in the collection are data files and experiment books kept by Pincus, the reports of his staff at the Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology, and manuscripts and correspondence relating to the many articles he wrote concerning the results of his research. The chronological arrangement of the Research Material series reveals the development of his interests and the thrust of his research at different periods in his life. The volume of writings in the Speech, Article, and Book File on the topic of the contraceptive pill suggests the importance of this development and some of the controversy which surrounded it.
The Diaries series contains two volumes, one from 1920, with original poetry, recounting the thoughts and experiences of Pincus as a youth of sixteen, and the other, from a few months in 1941, describe the research in which he was engaged and prospects for the future.
The Addition includes writings by Pincus; correspondence; glass slides containing data and results of fertility control experiments, clinical trials, and control groups in the form of tables, graphs, and charts; a scrapbook of newspaper clippings related to the birth control pill; and other papers.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in nine series:
Diaries, 1920-1967
Personal Correspondence, 1934-1967
Professional Correspondence, 1942-1967
Speech, Article, and Book File, 1926-1967
Research Material, 1933-1967
Notebooks, 1949-1963
Financial Papers, 1939-1967
Miscellany, 1923-1989
Addition, 1922-2006
Container List
- Diaries, 1920-1967 (Box 1-3)
  Diaries and appointment books.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Appointment books (Box 1)
    - 1957-1962, (6 vols.)
    - 1963-1965, (3 vols.) (Box 2)
    - 1966-1967, (2 vols.) (Box 3)
  - Biographical material, 1957-1967
  - Diaries, 1920, 1941, undated, (2 folders)
- Personal Correspondence, 1934-1967 (Box 4-7)
  Letters received and copies of letters sent.
  Arranged chronologically by year and alphabetically thereunder. Condolences on Pincus's death are arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - 1934-1948, undated, (8 folders)
  - 1953-1964, (11 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1965-1967, (6 folders) (Box 6)
  - Letters of condolence, 1967
    - "A-J", (9 folders)
    - "K-Z", (11 folders) (Box 7)
    - Unidentified
    - Telegrams
    - List of addresses
- Professional Correspondence, 1942-1967 (Box 8-134)
  Organized in the general arrangement in which it was kept by Pincus and his staff. The subseries reflect divisions in the records when they were received by the Library. Since these were working files, they are generally in reverse chronological order within folders.
  - General File, 1938-1967 (Box 8-104)
    Letters received and copies of letters sent, reports, memoranda, near print, and printed matter relating to Pincus's professional work.
    Arranged chronologically by year and alphabetically thereunder. Container 29 includes an article by Margaret Sanger that is also available on microfilm, shelf no. 21,422.
    - 1938-1951 (Box 8)
      - "A" miscellaneous, 1947-1951
      - Association for Study of Internal Secretions, 1951
      - "B" miscellaneous, 1951
      - Boes, Jean, 1949-1951
      - "C" miscellaneous, 1951
      - Ciba Foundation, 1951
      - Clark University, 1938-1943
      - "D" miscellaneous, 1951
      - "E" miscellaneous, 1951
      - "F" miscellaneous, 1945-1951
      - Foundation of Applied Research, 1951
      - "G" miscellaneous, 1951 (Box 9)
      - "H" miscellaneous, 1945-1951, (2 folders)
      - Hammond, John, 1949
      - Hoagland, Hudson, 1951
      - "I" miscellaneous, 1950-1951
      - "J" miscellaneous, 1951
      - "K" miscellaneous, 1951
      - "L" miscellaneous, 1950-1951
      - "M" miscellaneous, 1950-1951, (3 folders)
      - "N" miscellaneous, 1951
      - National Research Council, 1944-1950
      - New York Academy of Sciences, 1951
      - "O" miscellaneous, 1951
      - "P" miscellaneous, 1950-1951, (3 folders)
      - "R" miscellaneous, 1946-1951, (3 folders) (Box 10)
      - "S" miscellaneous, 1944-1951, (10 folders)
      - "T" miscellaneous, 1951, (2 folders)
      - "U" miscellaneous, 1951
      - Umbaugh, Ray, 1948
      - U.S. Pharmacopeia, 1948-1951, (2 folders)
      - United States Public Health Service, 1950-1951, (2 folders)
      - "W" miscellaneous, 1950-1951, (3 folders) (Box 11)
      - William R. Warner Co., 1951
      - Worcester State Hospital, 1957
      - "X-Z," 1950-1951, (2 folders)
    - 1952
      - "A" miscellaneous
      - "B" miscellaneous
      - Boston University
      - "C" miscellaneous
      - Ciba Foundation
      - "D-J" miscellaneous, (7 folders)
      - "K-N" miscellaneous, (4 folders) (Box 12)
      - National Science Foundation (L. Levin)
      - New York Academy of Sciences
      - "O-P" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Planned Parenthood Federation of America
      - "Q-V" miscellaneous
      - United States Public Health Service
      - "W" miscellaneous
      - Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology
      - "Z" miscellaneous
      - "A-B" miscellaneous (Box 13)
      - Boes, J.
      - "C" miscellaneous
      - Ciba Foundation
      - "D-E" miscellaneous
      - Endocrine Society
      - "F-J" miscellaneous, (5 folders)
      - "K-M" miscellaneous, (4 folders) (Box 14)
      - MacAndrews and Forbes Co.
      - Macmillan Co.
      - Macy Foundation
      - May, Ben
      - "N" miscellaneous
      - Navy
      - New York Academy of Sciences
      - "O-P" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Planned Parenthood Federation of America
      - "R-S" miscellaneous, (3 folders)
      - Southwest Foundation (Box 15)
      - "T-U" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - United States Public Health Service, (2 folders)
      - "V-W" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology
      - Worcester State Hospital
      - "X-Z" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
    - 1954-1955
      - "A-C" miscellaneous, (3 folders)
      - "D-E" miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 16)
      - Endocrine Society
      - "F-H" miscellaneous, (4 folders)
      - Hawaii
      - The Hormones, vol. III
      - "I" miscellaneous
      - "J-M" miscellaneous, (4 folders) (Box 17)
      - McCormick, K. D.
      - "N-P" miscellaneous, (3 folders)
      - Planned Parenthood Federation of America
      - Project Puerto Rico
      - "R-S" miscellaneous (Box 18)
      - Southwest Foundation
      - United States Public Health Service
        - Endocrine study
        - Radiosteroid committee
        - Steroid standards
      - "W" miscellaneous
      - Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology
      - "Y-Z" miscellaneous
    - 1955
      - Japan Trip
      - "R-S" miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 19)
      - Southwest Foundation
      - "T-U" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - United States Public Health Service
      - "V-W" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology
      - "Y" miscellaneous
    - 1956 (Box 20)
      - "A-C" miscellaneous
      - Ciba Foundation
      - "D-F" miscellaneous, (3 folders)
      - Ford Foundation
      - "G-I" miscellaneous, (3 folders)
      - India
      - "J" miscellaneous (Box 21)
      - Japan
      - "K-L" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - "M", (2 folders)
      - McCormick, K. D.
      - National Association of Mental Health
      - National Institute of Health
      - National Research Council
      - National Science Foundation (Box 22)
      - "O-P" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Patent applications
      - Planned Parenthood Federation of America International Planned Parenthood Federation
      - Population Council
      - Puerto Rico
      - "R" miscellaneous (Box 23)
      - Rock, John
      - "S" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Sanger, Margaret
      - Southwest Foundation
      - "T-U" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - United States Public Health Service, endocrinology study
      - "V-W" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology, interoffice memoranda
      - Worcester State Hospital
    - 1957 (Box 24)
      - "A" miscellaneous
      - Academic Press, Inc.
      - American Academy of Arts and Sciences
      - American Cancer Society
      - American Physiological Society
      - "American Societies" miscellaneous
      - Armour & Co.
      - Atomic Energy Commission
      - "B" miscellaneous
      - Boes, Jean
      - Books ordered
      - Boston University
      - "C" miscellaneous
      - Ciba Foundation
      - Ciba Pharmaceutical Products
      - "D-E" miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 25)
      - Estrogen Conference
      - "F" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Fan mail
      - "G" miscellaneous
      - Gamble, Clarence
      - "H" miscellaneous
      - Haiti (Box 26)
      - Hoagland, Hudson
      - "I-J" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Japan
      - "K-L", (2 folders)
      - Lasker, Mary
      - Layrentian Hormone Conference
      - "M" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Macy Foundation
      - Marrian, Guy
      - Massachusetts Society for Medical Research
      - McCormick, K. D. (Box 27)
      - Merck, Sharp & Dohme
      - "N" miscellaneous
      - National Association for Mental Health
      - National Research Council
      - National Science Foundation
      - New York Academy of Sciences
      - "O" miscellaneous
      - Office of Naval Research
      - Organon, Inc.
      - "P" miscellaneous (Box 28)
      - Pan-American Endocrine Conference
      - Parke-Davis Co.
      - Pincus
        - Lantern slides
        - Trips, (2 folders)
      - Planned Parenthood Federation of America
      - International Planned Parenthood Federation
      - Population Council
      - Puerto Rico
      - Purshottam, N.
      - "R" miscellaneous (Box 29)
      - Rock, John, (2 folders)
      - "S" miscellaneous
      - Sanger, Margaret.
        Article by Sanger also available on microfilm shelf no. 21,422
      - Schering Corp.
      - Sollins, I. V.
      - Southwest Foundation
      - Syntex S. A.
      - "T" miscellaneous (Box 30)
      - United States Public Health Service
        - Cancer chemotherapy
        - Endocrine study section
        - General
      - Upjohn Co.
      - "V" miscellaneous
      - Vineland Poultry
      - "W" miscellaneous
      - Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology
        - Interoffice memoranda
        - Staff manuscripts
        - Trustees
      - Worcester State Hospital
      - Young's Travel Service
      - "Z" miscellaneous
    - 1958 (Box 31)
      - "A-E" miscellaneous
      - "F" miscellaneous, (3 folders)
      - Fan mail
      - First International Endocrine Congress, (2 folders)
      - "G" miscellaneous
      - Gamble, Clarence
      - "H" miscellaneous, (6 folders) (Box 32)
      - Haiti
      - Hoagland, Hudson
      - Hormones and Atheascierosis Conference
      - "I-L" miscellaneous, (8 folders)
      - Lasker, Mary
      - "M" miscellaneous, (5 folders) (Box 33)
      - Mannian, Guy
      - McCormick, K. D.
      - "N" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Nassau Project
      - National Research Council
      - National Science Foundation
      - New York Academy of Sciences
      - "O-P" miscellaneous, (4 folders)
      - Planned Parenthood Federation of America
      - International Planned Parenthood Federation
      - Population Council (Box 34)
      - Puerto Rico
      - "Q-R" miscellaneous, (4 folders)
      - Rock, John
      - "S" miscellaneous, (5 folders)
      - Sanger, Margaret
      - Sollins, I. V.
      - Syntex S. A.
      - "T-U" miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 35)
      - United States Public Health Service
      - Upjohn Co.
      - "V-W" miscellaneous, (3 folders)
      - Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology
        - Interoffice memos
        - Safety committee
      - "Y-Z" miscellaneous
    - 1959 (Box 36)
      - "A-B", (2 folders)
      - "C" miscellaneous
      - Ciba Foundation
      - Ciba Pharmaceutical Products
      - "D-E" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Endocrine Society
      - "F" miscellaneous
      - Fan mail
      - "G" miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 37)
      - Gamble, Clarence
      - Guard, Hormez
      - "H" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Haiti
      - Hoagland, Hudson
      - "I" miscellaneous
      - "J" miscellaneous (Box 38)
      - Japan
      - "K-L" miscellaneous, (3 folders)
      - Lasker, Mary
      - "Ma" miscellaneous
      - "Mc-Mu" miscellaneous (Box 39)
      - McCormick, K.D.
      - Mercke, Sharp, & Dohme
      - "N" miscellaneous
      - National Research Council
      - National Science Foundation
      - Nelson, Warren
      - New York Academy of Sciences
      - "O-P" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Planned Parenthood Federation of America (Box 40)
      - International Planned Parenthood Federation
      - Puerto Rico
      - "Q-R" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Rock, John
      - "S-St" miscellaneous, (3 folders)
      - "Su-Sz" miscellaneous (Box 41)
      - Sollins, I. V.
      - Syntex S. A.
      - "T-U" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - United States Public Health Service
      - "V-W" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology
        - Public relations
        - Radiosotope Committee
      - Worcester State Hospital
      - "Y-Z" miscellaneous (Box 42)
    - 1960
      - "A-C" miscellaneous, (3 folders)
      - Committee for International Exchange of Persons
      - "D-E" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Fan mail (Box 43)
      - First International Endocrine Congress
      - "G" miscellaneous
      - "H" miscellaneous (Box 44)
      - Haiti Project
      - "I-L" miscellaneous
      - Lasker, Mary
      - "M" miscellaneous
      - McCormick, K. D.
      - "N-O" miscellaneous (Box 45)
      - Organon
      - "P" miscellaneous
      - Planned Parenthood Federation of America
      - Puerto Rico
      - "R" miscellaneous
      - Rock, John
      - "S" miscellaneous
      - Syntex S. A.
      - "T" miscellaneous (Box 46)
      - Tyler, Dr. David
      - "U" miscellaneous
      - United States Public Health Service, cancer chemotherapy
      - "V-W" miscellaneous
      - Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology, public relations
      - Worcester State Hospital
      - "X-Z" miscellaneous
    - 1961 (Box 47)
      - "A-F" miscellaneous, (7 folders)
      - Fan mail
      - "G-H" miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 48)
      - Haiti project
      - "I-J" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Japan
      - "K" miscellaneous
      - "L" miscellaneous (Box 49)
      - Lasker, Mary
      - "M-N" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Nelson,Warren
      - "O-P" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Planned Parenthood Federation of America
      - Puerto Rico
      - "Q" miscellaneous
      - "R-V" miscellaneous, (8 folders) (Box 50)
      - "W" miscellaneous (Box 51)
      - White House Conference on Aging
      - Worcester City Hospital
      - Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology
      - Worcester State Hospital
      - "Z" miscellaneous
    - 1962
      - "A-C" miscellaneous, (3 folders)
      - Ciba Foundation
      - "D-F" miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 52)
      - Fan mail
      - "G-H" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Haiti project
      - Huang, T. C.
      - "I-J" miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 53)
      - International Congress on Steroids
      - "K" miscellaneous
      - Kennedy, Anne
      - "L" miscellaneous
      - Lasker, Mary
      - "M" miscellaneous
      - Marmorston, Jessie
      - McCormick, K. D.
      - Medical Research Institute of Worcester
      - Mullen, H.J.
      - "N" miscellaneous (Box 54)
      - Nakao, Takeshi and Nakamura
      - National Foundation
      - Nelson, Warren
      - Newspaper clippings
      - "O-P" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Panicgua, Manuel
      - Parkes, Alan
      - Parthenis, Alexander
      - Pendleton, Satterthwaite, A.
      - Planned Parenthood Federation of America International Planned Parenthood Federation
      - Puerto Rico
      - "R" miscellaneous (Box 55)
      - Rice-Wray, Edris
      - "S-U" miscellaneous, (4 folders)
      - United States Public Health Service
      - "V-W" miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 56)
      - Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology
      - Worcester City Hospital
      - Worcester State Hospital
      - "Y-Z" miscellaneous
    - 1963
      - "A" miscellaneous
      - American Academy, seminar on Fertility and Population Problems
      - American Cancer Society
      - American Chemical Society symposium
      - Ayerst laboratories
      - Academic Press (Box 57)
        - The Hormones, vol. 4, (2 folders)
        - The Hormones, vol. 5, (2 folders) (Box 58)
      - "B" miscellaneous (Box 59)
      - Books ordered by Pincus
      - Bush, Jane E., grant proposals
      - "C" miscellaneous, (3 folders)
      - Ciba Foundation (Box 60)
      - Ciba Pharmaceutical
      - Coombe Chemical Corp.
      - "D-F" miscellaneous, (3 folders)
      - Fan mail
      - Food and Drug Administration
      - Foreign visitor status
      - France, Evelyn Susan
      - "G" miscellaneous
      - Garcia, Celso-Ramon
      - "H" miscellaneous (Box 61)
      - Haiti
        - Correspondence
          - Larague, Felix
      - Harvard
      - "I" miscellaneous
      - International Congress on Steroids, second congress
      - "J-K" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - "L"miscellaneous (Box 62)
      - Lasker, Mary
      - Lasker Foundation
      - Laurentian Hormone Conference
      - "M" miscellaneous
      - Marmorston, Jessie
      - McCormick, K. D.
      - Medical Research Institute of Worcester
      - Mercke Sharpe, & Dohme (Box 63)
      - Mexican Family Planning Association
      - "N" miscellaneous
      - Nakao, Takeshi
      - National Service Center, cancer chemotherapy
      - New York Academy of Sciences
      - Newspaper clippings
      - "O" miscellaneous (Box 64)
      - Organizations
        - "Am. Ac-Am. Ar, " miscellaneous
        - "Am. S-As" miscellaneous
        - "Na-Ni" miscellaneous
      - "P" miscellaneous
      - Pincus
        - Itineraries
        - Miscellaneous
      - Planned Parenthood Federation of America
      - International Planned parenthood Federation (Box 65)